This – is an interplanetary transport network!
And you think I can reach my home planet?
J.: I mean, probably?!
That's the spirit!
And this – is my probability tracer
solving tough spaceflight riddles.
What's the best path home,
optimizing fuel and time?
That's an insane
dynamical/combinatorial mixed problem.
And as we solve it, you learn to use
manifolds, weak stability boundaries,
periodic orbits, and many more spaceflight tools.
All shown in ways you
probably haven't seen before.
And we start with building the tracer.
I.. hope to get it right.
Because my friend needs a rescue.
I'm not judging, but how do you get here ..
running low on everything: the journey is over.
Still, it's a great example of what
to do when lost in outer space!
Step one: What makes 'getting home' so hard?
Imagine nothing else but you in a spaceship.
Getting from here to there is peanuts.
Fire and drift along a straight path.
Let's add a planet, and you swing by.
Is it still a great path?
Look into the future!
And for this two-body constellation,
looking means solving analytic expressions.
Which are pretty simple – give parameters,
and you get the Keplerian orbits.
Now, you can't see it, but the planet
moves around the gravitational center, too.
Energy and momentum conservation.
You will see it by adding more massive planets.
But except for some motions, you rarely find these
simple mathematically closed-form expressions.
Now we all have computers.
So, there is an easy prediction method for
many masses: numerical time integration.
The idea is simple.
Take the current gravitational forces
to guess tiny velocity changes.
And take the current velocities
to guess tiny location changes.
You guessed it: Newton's laws of motion.
This stepwise computation is prone to
errors and takes your computer some time.
Now, there is a tweak to speed up the
computation by splitting the simulation.
The spaceship is lightweight compared to the
planets, and so is its impact on their motion.
So, make a first run without the
spaceship and store the paths.
And then, play back the planet's motion in
the next run to get the spaceship's reaction.
That's much faster in total if you
want to compute many spaceships anyway.
Each new simulation only moves one spaceship
pulled by three gravitational forces.
Sounds great?
Here is the kicker.
To see if a path is a winner, predict the future.
Which, even for just one simulated spaceship,
gets harder the longer the journey.
Here, I fire a little bit, and
my route zaps all over the place!
With all the uncertainties about the real
world, longer simulations are hard to trust.
But no need for thrust issues here.
I can fire anytime to tune the path
and make a different winner, right?
Absolutely, but the next question
is: what is the best firing?
Say you are short on travel
time and propellant consumption.
To get the optimal route: You have to search
along all possible firings at any time!
That's a continuum of decisions!
Simply firing initially and then doing
nothing can't be the whole story?
Oh, and for my friend here,
there is an easy way home.
Fire relative to planet Silk in prograde direction
at this point to slow down relative to the Sun.
Wait a little bit.
Reach planet Blue's orbit.
Fire retrograde relative to Blue to slow
down while falling into an orbit around Blue.
From here on land! It's that easy.
And seriously, how else to get home.
That's a Hohmann transfer, which I
learned makes an ideal transfer orbit?
The problem is, it's too costly here.
Propellant runs out during the
'Low Blue Orbit' 'injection burn.'
So, what's the better sequence?
Let's compare all possible paths home,
considering all possible intermediate firings.
Spoiler: The continuity of firing
possibilities actually helps.
Spoiler spoiler: running special experiments,
low-energy routes will come up automatically.
And don't panic!
I keep this playground solar system
flexible in sizes and masses.
I want to see all local and global action at once.
Because this system revolves around education.
Step two: what's wrong with rays?
Forget about firing for now.
That's like spawning new rays.
There is a problem with ray
tracing in the first place.
I give an example.
Say you perform a gravity
assist maneuver, aka swing-by.
The speed before and after the swing-by
won't change relative to the planet,
but the path direction will.
Relative to the Sun, this changes the speed and
the orbital energy: you can reach farther out.
And here is the problem: After the swing-by,
the resolution of the ray package is lost.
Now, honestly, this spreading is nothing bad.
It's great for route controlling.
But it generates more non-sampled
space between the rays.
To fill in the details, shoot more rays.
But it doesn't solve the unbalanced resolution.
It's easy to miss a winner.
So why don't we build not a ray
tracer but a probability tracer?
Let's push spaceship-position
probabilities over a computational grid.
This gives a numerically equalized look,
and if a target is reachable, you see it!
Step three: tracing spaceship probabilities
First, let's get this right: tracing
probabilities answers a different question.
You don't look for precise routes
but whether there are any routes.
And then you know if it's
worth reconstructing a winner.
So, all I need is a probability
cloud that lives on a spatial grid.
And the algorithm tunes grid values to show
whatever infinitely many spaceships do.
Awesome, right?
Well, that's impossible.
Think of two probability clouds overlapping.
Nothing happens.
They pass without interaction.
And why should they?
They represent infinitely
many independent spaceships.
I hope you see the problem?
Both clouds overlap with
different velocity vectors.
So, which one tells the position-based
algorithm how to shift the grid values?
Which vector wins?
Or, for that matter, how to even
tell each cloud its velocity?
It's simple: A position-based description
contains not enough space to handle
arbitrarily multi-valued velocities.
The probability lives in position
and velocity space – the phase space.
And don't think of one magical phase
space size; it depends on the problem.
I give you an example.
These 1,000 particles make one point
in a 4,000-dimensional phase space.
Each coordinate stores unique
information about some particle.
You can make this point a blurred
blob to think collectively about
infinitely many variations of this experiment.
And here is the key.
Instead of tracing probabilities in this
high-dimensional n-particle phase space,
ask how likely to find any particle to be
in a given location and velocity range.
You can chase the probability in the same
phase space as that of the spaceship.
However, while the spaceship probability
passes without self-interaction,
the fluid does, and the probability shows it.
With enough particle interaction, they
struggle themselves to effectively
two-dimensional behavior –
they equilibrate locally.
And then, position-based fields make sense
– temperature, pressure, or probability.
Reduce to non-self-interaction, and
you need a four-dimensional grid.
So, the plasma or fluid side of the spectrum
are challenging for their own reasons.
But they also come with their own
solution methods that we can steal.
But it won't be easy!
Watch this!
This simulation runs on the huge amount of
200 x 200 cells …
by 200 cells …
by 200 cells.
1.6 billion cells to get this blocky blöb?
I was hoping for a full-blown statistical
analysis, but it's getting out of reach!
I mean, to investigate my
manifolds, I need a tracer.
Don't worry, things get worse.
Imagine a spaceship in one
dimension within a potential well.
The closer it gets to the
sides, the more it pushes back.
The phase space has two dimensions:
one for position and one for velocity.
And a probability density blob
reflects infinitely many spaceships.
Now, look at this.
As time passes, the probability mixes.
Yet, per tracer, the probability
density stays constant.
It doesn't diffuse with neighbor values.
The motion along position and
velocity compensate each other,
and arbitrary phase-space volumes are conserved.
So, this blob moves incompressibly, generating
infinite details without probability diffusion.
It looks like diffusion if you
don't look precisely, though.
And that's the problem.
My algorithm just stores grid
values – it doesn't look precisely.
To update these, you trace back
where the probability came from.
Which likely was somewhere between grid points.
So you have to guess these values.
This gives numerical softening or diffusion.
Then, why bother with all this?
Well, compared to ray tracing,
you equalize the resolution.
Although, under the hood, it
uses structured ray segments.
But the interpolation breaks the accuracy.
So, is all my hope in statistical
astrodynamics doomed to diffuse?
Thinking about it, doesn't it look like randomly
firing – that I have to implement anyway?
Also, I don't need the
probability but the reachability.
Do you get home – yes or no!
Step 4: tracing spaceship reachability
Careful!
Numerical diffusion can look like random firing.
But the probability blurs differently
– mainly along the phase space flow.
Random firing, however, means acceleration,
so it blurs along the velocity axis,
which then translates into position blurs.
And this tiny distinction matters.
We care about reachability but in phase space.
You don't want to reach planet
Blue's location at any cost.
You have a velocity window to reach as well.
Now, there is a computational
shortcut to handle that.
Think about reaching this spot
with the one-dimensional spaceship.
Random firing makes many
spaceships reach the goal.
But the fastest ones travel
on the blob's boundary.
They keep expanding the blob the
fastest by firing continuously.
Here, for the fastest way, fire towards
the goal and then fire backwards.
Now, there are electrical engines
built to fire continuously.
Essentially, they generate a relatively
low thrust over a long period of time.
In contrast, chemical engines give
higher thrust for shorter periods of time.
So, when I later solve a
continuous firing problem,
I just need to trace the boundary – great!
And realizing this, I wanted to build
an exact grid-based boundary tracer.
I put it in a longer version of this video.
And I partly managed to make it work, but it looks
like a gap-free prediction implies diffusion.
Making this whole grid thing is a debacle.
And I get the hint: To get my
tracer, I have to sacrifice.
Step 6: Building spray tracers.
Back to scratch.
I'm going to use rays –
with a statistical mindset.
And I wanna use my grid – somehow!
This is how I made it.
Remember: ray segments plus interpolation
crushes accuracy, so I use non-stop tracers.
And by tuning the phase point
updates, I control their accuracy.
This is how it works: The time integration
shifts position and velocity via rules.
Acceleration changes velocity,
which itself changes location.
Take the simplest form.
If you keep the current values constant
over a time step, the update is a product.
Reduce the timestep, and you
reduce the error accumulation.
But that's inefficient.
Higher-order methods, using
a mashup of test shots,
give similar accuracy with
less computational cost.
But you can do better.
Remember how the probability moved in phase space?
It conserved volume.
At least when the system itself conserves energy.
So, if you make your integrator share this
property, you get better long-time behavior.
But how to make it volume-conserving?
Look how the classical 1st order
method pushes this box over time steps.
The simultaneous shifts in position
and velocity make the box bigger.
So instead, make staggered shifts
along position and velocity.
The trick is to split the update
in volume-conserving shear motions.
Which here works since the acceleration
is independent of the velocity.
It won't stretch while shearing!
And this so-called symplectic integration
gives great long-time behavior.
Now, I'm not saying you should
always use symplectic integration.
A non-symplectic integrator ramped up to high
accuracy fulfills symplecticity naturally.
Both types converge to the
ground truth, just differently.
And the more information about the system
you bake into the integrator, the better.
Split in Kepler orbit and interplanetary
interaction steps if you have weak
interactions in planetary scenarios.
Make it fit your problem!
Now, to let my tracers mimic spaceships, I
activate randomly firing and limited fuel.
They also spawn offsprings to fill in the gaps.
And I built a grid that limits the spaceship
density in phase space and
so the computational time.
There is my grid! :)
So the rays explore, and the grid prunes.
That's all great, but eventually,
you send millions of rays.
Which is costly.
And that's where the statistical nature helps.
Remember: predictions are hard, and
slight nudges make huge impacts.
So, at least when getting first
inspiration for possible routes,
why bother predicting accurately
when you fire randomly anyway.
Numerical errors are easily overcompensated.
Just make sure the less accurate
blob covers the exact one.
You can artificially crank up the firepower
or take other creative global measures.
Ultimately, modifying the blob's global behavior
can be faster than making all tracers accurate.
This cheaply generates an
over-optimistic blob evolution,
but it definitely contains the winner route.
Which means you drastically limit the phase space
portion where to look for the exact solution!
Filtering impossible routes and optimizing
promising candidates is easily in post.
Step 7: Testflight
I'm not judging, but what on earth
is my friend doing near the Moon?
Anyway, getting home is probably a cakewalk.
Let's compute the reachability for
a continuously firing engine first.
Which I made comically strong
to highlight the maneuvers.
And remember: we just need
to trace the phase space
blob's boundary to find the quickest way home.
So, in the counting grid, I
can delete the tracers inside.
And just for this experiment, I made
the spaceship ultra heat resistant.
It allows for hefty aerobraking – and
reaching Blue's position is here enough.
And for the records, the projection of a phase
space blob's boundary looks like
a filled region in position space.
And now, let's run it.
There you have it: boundary tracing
answers a very specific question.
How to get home as quickly as
possible under continuous firing?
That's how!
Fire prograde relative to Moon to screw
out of Moon's gravitational significance.
And once you fall down to Blue,
I thought continuous retrograde firing eats
up the orbital energy most efficiently.
Or maybe firing against the
angular momentum works better.
Kind of like the inverse of
the maneuver for leaving Moon.
But the solution is surprisingly elegant.
Remember, I allowed for crashing into
Blue, and the code takes me at my words.
So, it fires a little retrograde, but
there is an overlayed firing to the right.
And it gets home, not in the first
encounter, but in the end much faster!
The idea is: if you slowly chew up the angular
momentum and still miss at the first encounter,
prepare yourself to at least
make it in the second attempt.
And since the electrical engine can
only push so much, it needs a little
bit more time and lever to do so, which
it gets by swinging to a higher altitude.
So, being less efficient at the
first encounter gives more time
to fight the angular momentum and crash home.
Now, if this maneuver is so great,
why didn't we leave Moon that way?
Well, simply because we didn't start in an
anti-crashing trajectory but in a circular
orbit, for which screwing out is the
fastest way when firing continuously.
But when landing, heat resistance allowed
for this rather "experimental" approach.
Surprisingly, it still works when
holding the firing direction constant.
This basically fakes a new potential
for a virtually non-firing spaceship.
It's like the classical rubber-sheet model tilted.
And my codes found this recipe simply by
pushing millions of dumb tracers around.
Anyway, the gridded boundary has some thickness.
So, checking nearby tracers; you're
quite flexible in getting home.
And don't forget it's a
numerical global solution method.
It gives a winner inspiration.
The route gets better by fine-tuning later.
Now that was fun, but …
What about non-continuous, stronger firings?
We could use stronger, continuous random
firing combined with a propellant cut-off logic.
But tracing out all 'technically
possible' paths really bows up the blob.
That's why I add a little bit of
sanity by firing when it is beneficial.
And to see this benefit, I shoot one-dimensional
spaceships into this potential well.
Here, the phase space paths
quickly start to squeeze.
This is because slower spaceships
spent more time in this well.
They are accelerated for longer,
building up more velocity change.
And since energy is here conserved, each
path is of constant energy per unit mass.
By the way, in this reference
frame, the well doesn't move.
So velocity and kinetic energy
are relative to that well.
Now, while firing, let's say all
the reaction mass pushed by the
engine is just one big mass pushed all at once.
In fact, let's make both
masses equal for simplicity.
Then, firing splits the big
mass into two smaller masses,
each following their own path, initially
differing by a fixed relative velocity.
Obviously, to get the most bang for the
buck, make the split when you can jump as
much energy levels as possible,
which is during the squeezing.
There are the points of highest speed along
each path, where kinetic energy climbs easiest.
The final speed-up or slow-down merely by firing
within a potential well is the Oberth effect.
Now, if you start out at higher velocity,
the Oberth contribution shrinks.
And this makes sense: passing so quickly,
there is not enough time to accelerate
much and build up greater velocity changes.
And so the squeezing fades
for higher initial speeds.
It's like leveling the well.
When passing a rock instead of a
planet, there is less Oberth effect.
On the other hand, taking your time is beneficial.
That's why the capture/escape path is
super sensitive to the Oberth effect.
That's the path that barely escapes.
Nonetheless, along each path, it's always
beneficial to fire at the fastest point.
And you get an intuitive visualization
by shooting non-firing blobs.
This makes it somewhat of
a squeezing detection tool.
Since the phase space volume doesn't change,
velocity-squeezing means position expansion.
Apply it inside the well?!
Once again, most squeezing
is at the fastest point.
Now, the question is, how does it
translate to the two-dimensional case?
It's quite similar!
First, let's take paths that share
the same point of closest encounter.
This connects them at their point of
highest velocity via a single burn.
That's great for later comparison.
So, shooting-off blobs that have the same size at
each path's slowest point, you see the
highest stretching at the fastest point.
Firing here splits the energy most effectively.
So, in the diagrams, I compare firing
at the fastest and the slowest point.
This is the Oberth effect.
Now, you can tell; among the paths,
the parabola is most effective.
And the reason simply comes down
to where the slowest point is.
On an ellipse, it is the outmost point.
And the more you fire at the fastest point, the
more it moves away, and the velocity lowers.
Until you get a parabola with zero velocity at
infinity – that's the route that barely escapes.
Fire more, and you get hyperbolas
with non-zero velocity at infinity.
And that's it:
Having non-zero velocity at the slowest points,
ellipses and hyperbolas give you more kinetic
energy when firing on their worst side.
This counters the Oberth effect.
You can still see a huge absolute energy increase.
But it would be huge already,
even without the Oberth effect.
And, of course, arriving on a parabola,
the post-firing hyperbola won't have the
highest energy compared to hyperbolic arrivals.
But the Oberth effect is "most effective."
So, in my simulation, I fire stronger aligned
with the velocity vector closer to the planet.
And I hope millions of routes
show the best combination.
You cannot always approach close to a parabola.
Now, back to my friend: let's get back to Moon!
The blob quickly explores phase space,
working on millions of possible
routes, and … I can't see anything!
So, just for learning, I
give you something better.
Let's sit on a Low Blue Orbit everywhere at once.
And remembering the Oberth
effect, I will fire twice.
One firing to get away from
Blue and another firing to
get captured by the Moon – nowhere in between.
On top, I vary the initial fire strength.
Each of these rings are millions
of spaceships, colored by strength.
Very soon, we hit Moon.
And here, we could make the second
firing to get captured by the Moon.
This family of routes is the Hohmann transfer
for a prograde or retrograde orbit around Moon.
It's pretty expensive fuel-wise
but quite fast: it's the first hit.
But let's keep going.
Every time the lines intersect with Moon,
a firing would conclude a family of routes.
And there are a lot of them –
I cannot even show them all!
But there is one type of family
that should draw your attention.
These lines slowly approach Moon.
Until some tracers get ballistically
captured by Moon without any firing.
Now, seeing the winner route doesn't tell
you why it is possible in the first place.
And this is really cool.
Let's rerun the ballistic trajectory, and
I want you to focus on this section here.
You see it?
We shoot off on an ellipse, but instead
of sticking to it, we get pulled aside.
Looks pretty much like the inverse of the
continuous firing solution we found before.
But we don't fire here!
So where does it come from?
Surprise, surprise: it's the
Sun – nature fires for us!
To get a first overview,
draw the potential energy!
And you clearly see: close to Blue, most
of the local dynamics are governed by Blue.
And the farther you go outwards, the more
the collective gravitational
pull shifts towards the Sun.
That's why we don't stick to the two-body ellipse.
In this first swing of the journey,
the Sun gets more relevant, and especially
the Blue-Moon interplay gets less relevant.
And there is a simple model that "captures"
this: the restricted circular three-body model.
It's a great playground with already rich
dynamical structures that explain a lot.
Now, to study the motion with the Sun always in
the same direction, co-rotate the reference frame.
This change in perspective alters the form of the
equations of spaceship motion when
written in co-rotating coordinates.
By how much are they altered?
Exactly as needed so that the generated
motion looks correct from "the outside."
I give you an example.
Here, I look at a resting mass from a
moving and rotating reference frame.
From that perspective, the mass
seems to get pushed around.
So, computing in this accelerating reference
frame, you have to add some forces.
Which combined push exactly as needed to
look like resting after back-transformation.
So, these forces only pop up for kinematic
reasons – once we mess with the coordinates.
You describe the same physical motion after
all – just from a fancy-dancy perspective.
But, as it goes, some of this mess is beneficial.
Here, the gravitational forces keep
both masses on circular orbits.
And focus on the smaller mass here.
Once co-rotating with the same rotational speed,
the centrifugal force makes
the mass apparently force-free.
In fact, you can compute the centrifugal
force anywhere by plugging in some position.
So, we can see it as a downhill push coming from
a position-based potential scaled with the mass.
And we can do the same with
the gravitational potential.
Obviously, bake them into an effective potential.
That's the potential the spaceship sees
in this co-rotating reference frame.
It's still pushed by the Coriolis force,
but the effective potential gives a hard
reachability limit for a given energy.
And so, a non-firing blob never exceeds the
zero-velocity lines for a given energy level.
You can lock the blobs to
certain energetic regions.
This potential is a great predictive tool.
And you can do even more.
Apparently, you can sit at the stationary
Lagrange points to rest
in the co-rotating system.
Let's isolate this point here and kick forward.
The Coriolis force immediately pushes
to the right of the relative velocity.
Eventually, we drift off.
But if we start next to the Lagrange
point and shoot off just right,
we can balance both forces to
orbit around the Lagrange point.
In a way, this is how my code computes this orbit.
The shooting method tweaks the kick-off to
nail down this orbit by rewarding periodicity.
And for this symmetric orbit type it's enough
to look for perpendicular axis crossings.
Now, when there is one orbit, there are more.
Tweaking not just the kick-off
velocity but the location as
well – meaning the whole phase space
point – you land on a different orbit.
Just enforce periodicity and some
distance measure towards the last orbit.
Then you performed 'numerical continuation'.
You have a solution point of a problem - here a
phase space point of an orbit - and
you find points on neighbor orbits.
Now, tracing such an orbit numerically,
you can check it's hard to stay on them.
They are surrounded by regions in
phase space that, once you sit on them,
lead you to the orbit or away from
it – stable or unstable manifolds.
These are the structures I'm looking for.
Why?
Because they tell you in advance what you get.
Take the one-dimensional spaceship
with a hill-shaped potential.
Starting anywhere makes you follow the flow.
Starting at the equilibrium leads you nowhere.
This point is not an orbit,
but let's pretend it is equivalent as
in: once you sit on it, you stay on it.
A stationary feature of the phase space motion.
And the stable and unstable
manifolds are nothing more
but curves that lead you to and from that point.
Though you never reach it, it would
take an infinite amount of time.
But they are helpful as they tell
you what happens close to them.
You know in advance that once you ride close
to the stable manifold, you will curve away,
following either side of the unstable manifold.
That's the skeleton of the phase space motion.
Also, taking slightly different paths is great to
generate some waiting time while
ending up at the same location.
Both points are great for planning a spaceflight.
Remember: to catch up with Moon, you need the
right position and velocity at the right time.
And no matter how energetic you start out,
you need to build up angular
momentum relative to Blue as well.
That's why the Hohmann transfer
comes with a strong second burn.
But the manifolds tell us how to get it for free.
Part of the stable manifold reaches down to Blue.
You can follow close to it, having enough
energy but still low angular momentum.
But looking at the unstable manifold,
we know there must be the right "curve
away" bringing us up here in time –
having much more angular momentum.
Under the hood, it's the effective
potential and the Coriolis force pushing us.
Also note: we curve away close to the
outside of the stable manifold tube.
You can guess what happens being inside the tube.
Now, having the angular momentum,
we need to approach Moon just right,
which doesn't even exist in the three-body
system where these manifolds come from.
Well, closer to Blue and Moon,
their restricted three-body system
with its manifolds is more relevant.
So, hopping manifolds is the name of the game –
and we follow the stable manifold to the Moon.
Now, approaching Moon statistically, some tracers
get temporarily captured for a number of cycles.
And to get the essence of
this, go ahead systematically.
Any passing trajectory has a point
of its first closest encounter.
And so you start at an angle with a perpendicular
kick-off – here in prograde direction.
If it wouldn't be for Blue, you would then
make an ellipse with a predefined eccentricity.
But since Blue spits in the soup, count the
number of revolutions around Moon until escape.
For that, you check the Kepler energy sign of the
local spaceship-Moon system after each revolution.
So, n-stable orbits make n revolutions
around Moon with a negative energy
sign at the cut section – all without
making a full revolution around Blue.
That's the simulation cut-off time.
Repeat this experiment for the
next points along the cut section,
and you find changes in the n-stability.
Now, let's focus on 0- and 1-stable
orbits and their boundaries.
These boundary points collected for all
angles for the given eccentricity
make the weak stability boundary.
And along this boundary, you find
points that will crash into Moon.
Now, these sets of points
are great for two reasons:
First, obviously, they tell you where to
be in phase space to get captured by Moon.
This is similar to the effective
potential and manifold ideas.
Second, while sometimes coinciding with
manifold points, they make a more general tool.
Manifolds are great; they split energetic regions,
making it easy to see where
stuff goes in and goes out.
But they need orbits to emerge from.
And the orbits need Lagrange
points to emerge from.
And these Lagrange points here need the restricted
circular three-body system to emerge from.
When you go with a restricted four-body system,
the Lagrange points and the
emerging structures are no more.
The three body sub-systems are
disturbed by the remaining mass.
And so you don't exactly rest in
the co-rotating reference frame.
But there are still sensitive regions, and
the manifolds still make a great guide.
The weak stability boundary – you can
build it for more general systems directly.
You simply count revolutions
– however, they came about.
It's just time-dependent now.
But honestly, if nature gently carries you close
to Moon, fire a little bit to safely stay with it.
That's how you blow up the n-stability.
You jump from the 1-stability
for the eccentric approach to
the above 10-stability for the circular orbit.
These are the phase space
structures for low-energy
transfer to the Moon – or anywhere else?
Starting from a Low Blue
Orbit fire to get up here.
Then, follow inside the stable manifold tube and
slip through the orbit into the unstable manifold.
If we are lucky, it overlaps with
the stable manifold of planet Yellow.
But we aren't.
They don't even come close.
Visualizing the speed by an upward shift,
you can guess the phase space distance.
So, you look for a
cost-effective two-burn hop-over.
That's an intermediate Hohmann transfer.
From here on, it is the inverted
sequence to a Low Yellow Orbit.
This sequence of manifolds is part of
the interplanetary transport network.
Now, as fancy as it looks, it's hard to see if
it's better than a classical Hohmann transfer.
So, let me convince you with a much more intuitive
Blue-Moon example that such routes can be cheaper.
Remember: Since, all we got
to do is getting up here,
let's get there via gravity assist by Moon itself.
The Hohmann transfer would need a strong
retrograde burn to get captured by Moon.
The low-energy ballistic transfer
gets you captured for free.
It just takes some time.
That's the trade-off.
And for a fair comparison, both missions
lead here to a 2-stable capture.
Also, the Coriolis force and effective potential
work in our favor in the fourth quadrant as well.
Here, the angular momentum keeps
building up in the right way.
So you can expect similar routes to the Moon.
You can also use inner routes.
That's when you hop on Blue-Moon's
inner stable manifold – either via
a Hohmann transfer or the low thrust spiral.
This carries you up to the Moon.
And to show what else is possible, the orbit
families we found are linked to other families.
The planar Lyapunov orbits – the ones I have shown
before – bifurcate into Halo orbits and many more.
Each having its own manifolds.
It's a mess.
It's helpful, nonetheless.
Things seem cluttered from time to time,
leaving you wondering if you ever make
it: there is always a way, always!
Step 8: Time to get home.
This is the problem:
My friend makes an elliptic orbit at planet Silk
with enough propellant to reach planet Blue.
But not enough to get into
a circular Low Blue Orbit.
Oxygen is limited.
And hull integrity is … we shouldn't aerobrake.
So, to lose energy, we need
clever swing-by's, possibly fired.
Speaking of firing:
On the first elliptic passage – firing closest
to the planet doesn't make the best
departure angle relative to the Sun.
Not all of the Oberth speed boost
goes in the backwards direction.
That's why the best firing point
makes an inefficient compromise.
Simply waiting gives better departure
angles, and you can reach "farther down."
Then again, the planets must align for
great swing-bys – that's a phasing problem.
This is how I made it.
I divided the space in an interplanetary
part and local planetary parts.
These control the tracer resolutions.
Now, the tracers without contact
didn't make it to Blue in time.
So, the winner route is hidden
in the uninvestigated shadows.
These I explore with higher
resolution sampled from the recording.
Eventually, I iterate along encounters.
Now, at planet Blue, some tracers have enough
propellant to decelerate onto the goal orbit.
That makes a complete route.
And since tiny changes make a huge difference,
you get infinitely many routes per family.
Simply pick a suitable route from an
efficient cluster, trading time vs. propellant.
This route makes five revolutions around planet
Silk before leaving for the inner planets.
Here, a swing-by at Blue
takes away a lot of energy.
Still, it needs additional firing to
make the final arc hit home just right.
If you can invest more travel time, take
this route and save even more propellant.
The Blue-Yellow double swing-by
takes away even more energy.
And then just wait until you catch up with Blue.
Both variants are much better than the
instant and optimal Hohmann transfer.
And as expected, since I encouraged
Oberth-promoting swing-bys,
the winners are mostly composed
of locally efficient maneuvers.
And if you color it not by cluster but
by interplanetary segment, you get this.
The more swing-bys you consider, the easier it
is to get the final arc close to Blue's orbit.
Making it easier to arrive
on a low-energy manifold.
By the way, this is another
riddle I'm trying to solve.
Maybe you can help me with that
… if you enjoyed the video?
Thank you for watching!
Oberth and out.